We've already used loops over indices, when working with a single string or
سابقا از چرخه ها با بهره گیری از ضرایب استفاده کردیم،وقتی با تک string کار میکردیم یا
a single list.
یک تک لیست.
In this lecture, we're going to use loops over indices
در این مبحث،قصد داریم که روی ضریب ها از چرخه استفاده کنیم
to access the items at corresponding positions of two different lists.
که به آیتم های موقعیت های مربوطه از دو لیست مختلف دست یابیم.
And the characters at corresponding positions of two different strings.
و کاراکترها در موقعیت های مربوطه از دو string مختلف.
We will begin by implementing this function named sum_items.
با به کار گیری تابع sum_items کارمان را شروع میکنیم.
It takes two parameters, list1 and list2 which are both lists of numbers.
دو پارامتر به خود میگیرد ،list1 وlist2 که هر دو لیست اعداد هستند.
And it returns a list of numbers.
و لیست نمرات را تحویل میدهد.
The job of the function is to return a new list, in which each
نقش تابع این است که لیست جدیدی را ارائه دهد،که در آن هر
item is the sum of the items, at the corresponding position of list1 and list2.
آیتم مجموع آیتمها در موقعیت مربوطه list1,list2باشد.
Let's explore what is meant by the phrase corresponding position.
حالا تحقیق میکنیم که منظور از موقعیت مربوطه چیست.
If list 1 refers to a list with 3 elements values 1, 2,
اگر list1 سه عضو 1و2و3
and 3, and list 2, refers to a 3 element list with values 2, 4, and 2.
و list2سه عضو 2و4و2 را داشته باشد.
Then, there are three elements in each list with indices 0, 1 and 2.
آنگاه،سه عضو در هر لیست با ضریب های 0و1و2 داریم.
When we say that we want to consider the corresponding elements of list1 and list2,
وقتی که میگوییم که میخواهیم اعضای مربوطه list1,list2،
we're referring to the elements or the items, which are at the same index.
منظورمان اعضا یا آیتم های با ضریب یکسان است.
For example, at index 0, there are values 1 and 2, and those are summed to get 3.
مثلا،در ضریب 0،مقادیر 1و2 را داریم که جمعشان میشود3.
At index 1, there are values 2 and 4, which are summed to get 6.
در ضریب1،مقادیر2و4 را داریم که وقتی که جمعشان بزنیم میشود5.
And at index 2, there are values 3 and 2, which, when summed, yield 5.
و در ضریب2،مقادیر3و2،که وقتی جمع زده میشود،5 را به دست میدهد.
This makes up the new list, which is returned by this function.
این لیست جدیدی را میسازد که تابع تحویل میدهد.
Now, let's write this code.
حالا برنامه را بنویسیم.
We're going to, return a new list, and so
قصد داریم که لیست جدیدی را تحویل دهیم،و بنابراین
we'll create a variable sum list that will initially refer to an empty list.
متغیری با عنوانsum list به وجود میاوریم که در ابتدا لیستی خالی است.
This list will be built up one element at a time,
این لیست یکی یکی اضافه میشود،
through the course of the function.
از طریق دوره ای که تابع پیش میبرد.
We saw when we were looking at the example,
دیدیم که وقتی به مثال نگاه میکردیم،
that we use indices to access the elements of list 1 and list 2, so
از ضریب ها برای دسترسی به اعضای list1 , list2استفاده میکنیم،پس
we want to loop over the indices, for i in range of length of.
میخواهیم از طریق ضریب ها،برای i در دامنه طول لیست، چرخه بسازیم.
And now we can pass one of the two lists in here as an argument.
و اکنون میتوانیم یکی از این دو لیست را در اینجا به عنوان مولفه رد کنیم.
List 1 and list 2 will have the same lengths because of the precondition to
مطابق با آن چه که نشان داده شد
this function, shown above.
list1 ,list2 یک طول دارند.
Therefore, I can pick either of the two lists, and I'll choose list 1.
بنابراین،هر یک از دو لیست را میتوانم انتخاب کنم.
To choose the length of list 1.
برای انتخاب  طولlist1
That means that range will generate values 0, 1 up to,
که به این معنی است که دامنه مقادیر0و1 تا
but not including the length of the list.
طول لیست ولی نه خود طول لیست را شامل میشود.
In the body of the loop, we want to access list one at position I and
میخواهیم که در بدنه چرخه به i در list1 و
list 2 at position I, and sum them.
list2 درموقعیت i دسترسی یافته و آنها را با هم جمع کنیم.
Once we've calculated the sum, we want to add that to the sum list.
وقتی که جمع را حساب کردیم،میخواهیم که آن را به sum list بیافزاییم.
The list depend method, can be used to add that sum to the end of the sum list.
روش متکی به لیست،برای افزودن مجموع به انتهای sum list استفاده میشود.
That's the only thing we need to do in the body of the for loop.
این تنها کاری است که نیاز ست که در بدنه چرخه for انجام دهیم.
Once the for loop has finished executing and
وقتی که چرخه for به پردازش پایان داد و
exits, then we can return the sum list.
خارج شد،آنگاه میتوانیم که sum list ا تحویل دهیم.
Now let's run the example function call.
اکنون فراخوانی تابع نمونه را به جریان میاندازیم.
First, run the module, and then in the shell, call the function.
ابتدا،برنامه را به جریان بیاندازید،و آنگاه shell را،تابع را فراخوانید.
And we can see that it returns a list with values 3, 6, and 5.
و میتوانیم ببینیم که لیستی را با مقدارهای3و6و5 تحویل میدهد.
Let's implement one more function.
یک تابع دیگر را به کار بگیریم.
The name of this function is count_matches, and
نام تابع count_matches است،و
it involves two strings.
دو string دارد.
It has two string parameters, s1 and
دو پارامتر stringی s1 و
s2 and returns an int which is the number of positions in string s1,
s2 داشته و عدد صحیحی را تحویل میدهد که تعداد موقعیت ها در string موسوم به s1،
that became the same character at the corresponding position of s2.
کهدر موقعیت مربوطه s2 همان کاراکتر شده است.
For sample, for string ape and string ate,
به عنوان نمونه،برای stringهای به نام apeوate،
there are two characters in common.
دو کاراکتر مشترک است.
At index 0, there are a's, and index 2 there are e's.
در ضریب0 aو در ضریب 2 e.
For the strings head and hard.
برای string های head ,hard.
There are also two characters in common, the h's at index 0 and the d's at index 3.
در اینجا نیز دو کاراکتر مشترک هست،h در ضریب صفر و d در ضریب 3.
The first step for implementing this function, is to create an accumulator.
اولین قدم برای به کار گیری این تابع ایجاد جمع کن است.
I'll name it num matches, and it will initially refer to the value 0.
آن را num matches میخوانم،و مقدار اولیه اش صفر قرار میدهم.
That variable will accumulate the number of matches.
آن متغیر تعداد حروف یک جور را جمع میکند.
We saw that when we looked at the example,
در نگاهی به مثال آن را مشاهده کردیم،
we were comparing the string characters at the same index.
مقایسه بین کاراکترها با ضریب یکسان بود.
That means, we are gonna write our loop over the indices of the strings.
معنی این سخن این است که میخواهیم که چرخه خود را بر پایه ضریب های string بنویسم.
So we'll use range, starting from position 0, or value 0,
پس از دامنه استفاده خواهیم کرد،با شروع از وضعیت 0،یا مقدار صفر،
up to the length of the string s1.
تا طول string به نام s1.
And what we'd like to do is compare the character of the the string of s1,
و آن چه که میخواهیم انجام دهیم مقایسه کاراکتر string به نام s1،
so if s1 at index I, is equal to the string s2 at index I.
پس اگر s1 در ضریب i برابر با s2 در ضریب i باشد
Then we found a match, and
آنگاه که معلوم شد که یکی هستند،و
we can increment the num_matches variable, adding 1 to it.
میتوانیم که به متغیر num_matches یکی یکی اضافه کنیم.
Once the loop has finished executing and
آنگاه که چرخه به پردازش پایان داد و
we've passed over every character in the strings, then num_matches is returned.
از تک تک کاراکترهای string ها گذر کردیم،آنگاه num_matches تحویل داده میشود.
Let's run the example function calls.
فراخوان نونه تابع را به جریان بیاندازیم.
First the ate and ape example returns 2, and
ابتدا مثال ate,ape عدد2 را تحویل میدهد،و
then the head and hard example, also returns 2.
آنگاه مثالhead ,hard عدد 2 را تحویل میدهد.